I don’t think I could have written this video without the help of coffee. The
performance-enhancing drug of anyone trying to get stuff done, blue collar workers,
and college students on deadlines. And we are not alone. Ever since coffee first exploded
onto the global scene, it has been fueling scientific breakthroughs, inspiring art
and poetry and keeping us going through good times and bad. But coffee is never mentioned
in ancient history- so where did it actually come from, and how did it end up everywhere?
Today we are following the story of coffee from the very beginning. Tracing its path through
history, and covering the fascinating characters who led the way, played a role in its development
or tried anything to stop its meteoric rise. Whatever you think you know about the history of
coffee- the real story is a thousand times wilder. So we’re loading up on caffeine
and diving in. Today on OTR. In the year 1735, the city of Leipzig
in today’s Germany was in a full-blown panic over the popularity of a new drink known as coffee.
Now this was entirely generational. Like, the same way our parents might have reacted
to our taste in music, older Germans thought this trendy new beverage was the height of depravity,
and a sign that things were going downhill fast in polite society.
The local newspaper- the first daily newspaper in the entire world- referred to the young generation
as “coffee-drinking apes.” Doctors said that coffee could lead to psychological disorders,
and since people who drank the stuff used to socialize and talk about complicated subjects,
well obviously that was a danger to society’s women, who were quickly banned from Leipzig’s
cafes. A ban that would be largely ignored. The biggest of the cafes was known as
Zimmermann’s, said to be as lively and energetic as any bar today. Especially on Friday evenings,
when the city’s musical director Johann Sebastian Bach would assemble a group
of musicians and put on a free concert. Bach’s performances at Zimmermann’s were
less stoic concertos than rambunctious parties. And his most popular piece written for the Friday
occasions was known as Be Still, Stop Talking- or more commonly, the Coffee Cantata. It was
basically a 25-minute long mini-opera, telling the story of a young woman fighting with her
conservative father about her love for coffee. He tries everything to get her to stop- taking
away her possessions, her food, her favorite clothing…but she will not budge. Finally he
tells her that if she won’t give up coffee, he’ll ban her from getting married. So she agrees,
and finds a nice husband. But in secret she adds a clause to the marriage contract that he
must provide her with all the coffee she could possibly desire. The performance ends with the
three main characters all joining hands to sing a song about how drinking coffee is just the best.
And no matter how much the old generation didn’t like it, pretty soon everyone else would agree.
By today, it is impossible to imagine a world without coffee. We consume more than 2.3 billion
cups per day from one side of the planet to the other. Coffee is essential to life here
in Thailand. In South America and Northern Europe, where in Finland, it is a requirement for workers
to be given two coffee breaks every single day. A trip to Italy means mainlining espresso,
and no visit to Ha Noi would be complete without egg coffee or the famous coconut coffee smoothie.
There is Yuanyang in Hong Kong diners. Turkish coffee essential in Istanbul, and café Cubano,
iconic of course in Cuba. Coffee can be served from the pot in the United States,
or made into an art form in Melbourne, Australia. We make our coffee at home before heading out.
Bring our laptops to work at a café, and of course, when we meet our friends we go out for
coffee. As you saw on the TV show Friends, and a countless number of other television programs
or movies where coffee is the centerpiece of everyday life. Or at least something without which
getting through the day would be unthinkable. But given that as recently as the 18th century,
coffee  was a brand-new arrival, how did all of this happen?
Now- full disclosure, if you watch every single OTR video, we have covered this next part before-
at least in a quick two-minute segment. Honestly everyone on YouTube does the history of coffee. It
is maybe the most common topic I have ever encountered while working on one of these
“history of” stories, which is crazy because we’ve gotten into staples like rice and bread.
The origin of coffee is by now, very well known; at least the legend about a farmer named Kaldi in
Ethiopia, who one day watched as his goats ate a bunch of berries. The goats started jumping around
and acting crazy so Kaldi took the berries to a local temple, to be examined by monks. The Holy
Men took a look and said that it was the work of the devil, so they threw the berries into
a fire where they started to roast and smell incredible. The monks scooped out the berries,
put them in a bowl and covered them in water to cool them down, and thus was born coffee.
And that is pretty much the story that’s everywhere on the internet. But it was
made up a few hundred years later as part of a marketing campaign to sell Italian coffee.
So what is the real story? Let’s start at the beginning.
Around 700 years ago, a group of elders from Ethiopia’s Oromo Tribe met in what’s
now Madda Walabu to codify a set of laws, and agree on the policies to govern a large
and growing East African territory. These elders were not chieftains or
members of royal families. They were elected- the Oromo one of the world’s first true democracies,
at least since the fall of the Roman Republic. Their society was advanced; over thousands of
years they’d developed their own language, culture and religion, known as Waaqeffanna.
In ancient Waaqeffana mythology the world was created by a god named Waaqa, a benevolent deity
who cared for his people. And when the first man died, Waaqa buried him in the ground and wept, and
from his tears came a plant that would be the most sacred, the most essential to the Oromo people.
What we now call coffee. Every Oromo ceremony or political gathering
involved prayers or blessings over bowls of coffee berries. No contracts could be formalized or
conflicts resolved without some sharing of coffee, and weddings would begin with a new bride biting
open coffee berries, which would then be cooked in clarified butter and given out to all guests.
But the main use of coffee was not ceremonial. It was functional. Whenever Oromo hunters would head
out to find prey, when warriors would leave for battle or even when farmers would start a day in
the fields, they would grind ripe coffee berries in a mortar and pestle, add in some animal fat,
and form the mixture into balls the size of quarters. They’d fill leather pouches with
these coffee snacks and this would provide the main sustenance for Oromo tribesmen…an early
power bar packed with nutrients, fat, sugar, and of course, a massive pop of caffeine.
Now the Oromo, at least for most of history, did not actually drink coffee- but for the sake
of this story that doesn’t really matter, because that meeting of the elders in 1350 would prove to
be the big bang that would lead us to the present. Basically, over the next few years Oromo traders
would spread out across the region, establishing contacts and building relationships with
neighboring tribes in Ethiopia and as far as South Sudan and today’s Eritrea and Djibouti.
On one of these trading missions they would find their way into a tiny settlement in
extreme isolation, the home of a people called the Kafficho, who lived deep in the forest and to that
point had shunned all contact with outsiders. The Kafficho had their own tradition for using
coffee. One that as far as we can tell, they developed completely independently a
very long time ago. It involved removing the seed, or coffee bean from the fruit,
then roasting the beans in a pan over a flame. After that, they’d be ground and then soaked
in water in a specialized clay pot. This would then be heated again with salt, clarified butter
and herbs added in to the mixture. The local people would drink this
concoction constantly- serving it several times a day along with their staple food,
a flatbread made from Ensete, or false banana flour. The bread would be softened in this hot
coffee liquid and that was the Kafficho diet. Now I don’t know why Oromo traders were allowed
to visit the Kafficho settlement. For hundreds of years before and after,
the tribe would live in complete isolation, shunning all contact with outsiders. But
luckily for all of us, they made at least this one exception, and it would change the world.
Almost immediately this new form of drinkable coffee would sweep across Ethiopia, becoming a
sensation among the Oromo people and catching on wherever they would trade, just in time for
the civilization’s golden age and rapid expansion. And while that is just the beginning of the story
and we still have a long way to go, I can’t think of a better excuse for us to take a break for our
first cup of coffee.
The Ethiopian coffee ceremony is one of those things that everyone should get to experience.
I was lucky enough to get to do this a thousand times in Ethiopia, when Daria and I spent a
month there a few years back. But honestly even thousands of miles away it’s still pretty much the
same idea, and the same incredible coffee.
It can take a solid two or three hours for a proper coffee break in Ethiopia,
and that’s the idea. To relax, talk to the people around you and just exist while fresh coffee beans
are washed, roasted over coals, crushed and then brewed. Then you don’t just drink your
cup and leave…you stick around until the Jebena is empty. Then filled back up and emptied again.
So, we did this at
another place in our History of Breakfast video last year, and I thought about- we don’t like to
repeat things…we cannot do the History of Coffee without Ethiopian. We just can’t. I think- I’m
going to talk a little bit, because this is really hot and I’m going to give it a second before we
take our first sip. Let me talk you through what we have. Coffee- most important thing in any
Ethiopian home is the Jebena. Is that right? Most important thing, every family has to have one,
you pass it down to your kids, this is the coffeepot. So we were just talking off camera,
when we went to Ethiopia, my biggest regret, we should have brought one back with us. It
would have collected all the dust though. I know- we just order on Grab. So…coffee,
this is going to be barley, and then this is something that we ordered. Barley’s just
going to be a snack you eat with coffee. This we ordered- Chechebsa. So this is going to be
flatbread in clarified butter and berbere, which is the quintessential Ethiopian spice blend. This
is kind of a breakfast food, you’ll have this with coffee, but in Ethiopia…is it good? Oh,
it’s delicious. Mmm.
You know, I always forget how many countries are in Africa, because it changes depending
on…South Sudan is a relatively newly recognized country, Western Sahara…but it’s 55 or 56 I think.
Somewhere around 55 or 56. All of them, except for one, was a colony of a foreign country, a European
country. The only one country that was not colonized was Ethiopia. So it really is like
going back in time. It is so unlike anywhere else I have ever been. The whole country smells like-
like this. So…burning- again, it’s Biblical- frankincense and myrrh is what they burn to
send a signal guests or visitors or whoever is driving by, “hey, we’ve got coffee,
come on in.” It’s a welcoming thing. And it’s that, combined with the smell of the coffee beans
roasting…it’s a welcome thing. So that’s how our driver knew we could stop there, because they had
the thing smoking outside? I think they were just businesses. I think he knew he could stop there
because it was a coffee shop.
From a scientific perspective, the evolution of caffeine is fascinating. It is a genetic anomaly-
an adaptation that is incredibly complex and yet is so ingenious that over the last 70 million
years it’s shown up completely independently all across the planet, from cacao in Peru
and Colombia, to the tea plant in the Himalayan foothills, Guarana in Brazil, the Kola Nut in West
Africa and of course, coffee in today’s Ethiopia. I’ll make this fast but basically caffeine is
an alkaloid compound; technically C8 H10 N4 02. It protects a plant from predators like
insects by causing a bitter flavor, and even acting as a toxin if consumed in high enough
doses. When coffee leaves and berries fall onto the forest floor they release caffeine
which poisons the topsoil, preventing any other plants from taking root, so all the nearby water,
nutrients and sunlight belongs only to them. And maybe the craziest effect is that in the
nectar of coffee flowers, there is exactly enough caffeine to get honeybees addicted,
but not enough to cause them any harm. This means that in an entire biosphere,
bees that have tasted coffee will choose that plant to pollenate and ignore everything else.
Literally becoming hooked on caffeine. As far as we are concerned the way it
works is basically that during the day as we use energy our brain releases adenosine,
which builds up and makes us feel tired. We are calibrated to fill up our reserves of adenosine,
get drowsy and fall asleep. But caffeine blocks our adenosine receptors. It literally prevents us
from receiving the signal that we are exhausted. Obviously this does wear off, all of the adenosine
hits us at once and we crash hard, unless we just keep drinking coffee.
Here is why I bring all of this up. In the 14th century, the country of
Yemen had become the global center of a religious movement known as Sufi,
or Sufism. Essentially a deeply spiritual form of Islam in which followers become closer to God
through chanting, music and most of all, dancing; hours upon hours of constant motion, most famously
represented by the whirling dervishes of the Mevlevi Order. The longer one can maintain
repetitive and exhausting physical activity, the higher the ascension into the spiritual plane,
and the dancing and devotionals can go on all night. Now all of that might seem tangential,
until we take a look at a map, and see how close Yemen actually is to the country of Ethiopia. And
after coffee began to spread through East Africa it wasn’t long before it crossed the Red Sea,
and Sufi followers discovered the same thing most of us have at some point in our lives…when
you need to stay up late dancing, coffee helps. And this brings us to the next part of our story.
Around the end of the 14th century coffee arrived in Yemen, and we know it must have
caused a sensation, because all at once we see an explosion of writing from the Port of Aden,
describing a magical drink fueling Sufi prayers. At first this was referred to as Buna, the name
in Ethiopian. But soon enough it would given a new name, from old Arabic, translating to “the
Wine of Life.” This would be pronounced Qahwah. Beyond giving coffee its name, the Yemenites also
domesticated the plant, cultivating massive gardens of coffee trees. And yes, in nature,
it is a tree- growing in Ethiopia up to 12 meters tall. But in Yemen farmers began the
practice of trimming branches to keep it small enough to harvest by hand even at maturity.
With easy access from across the Red Sea, and a new homegrown supply, Yemen had plenty of coffee,
so it began to travel, and the first place it would be taken was the Holy City of Mecca, brought
along by Sufi Muslims on the Hajj or pilgrimage. And here we also know it caused a sensation
because we also see an explosion in writing, with a poem found in Mecca dating back to the 15th
century saying, and I quote, “Coffee is our gold. Wherever it is served, one enjoys the society of
the noblest and most generous men.” End quote. It was also in Mecca where coffee would
first be sold to the public, the very first cafés or coffeeshops opening to service
pilgrims from Yemen, then from everywhere. And since pilgrims arrived in the city from
all across the Muslim world, coffee spread fast- so fast that within ten years of the first record
of coffee anywhere outside Ethiopia, it was the drink of choice across Egypt, the Arabian
Peninsula, the Middle East and Ottoman Turkey. And all of that coffee had to come from somewhere.
It seems to have occurred to the Yemeni people pretty much from the beginning that coffee had
commercial potential, and those farms we mentioned were not just planted for domestic consumption.
By the time we see that first café in Mecca, Yemen already had laws on the books forbidding
the export of raw seeds, or live coffee plants. Only coffee beans that had already been sterilized
were allowed to be taken abroad, and the punishment for violating this policy was death.
A sentence apparently carried out more than once. To make absolutely certain no plant-able coffee
beans slipped through, all international trade in the country was routed through only one port,
where every single boat could be and was thoroughly searched.
This was the port of Al-Mocha, which is why all across the Muslim world coffee took on the
nickname Mocha, or “Mocha”. Anyway.
Yemen might have had a coffee monopoly and Mecca might have been the place where it
caught on with the masses but before long- the capital of coffee culture was about to emerge
in a city called Istanbul. According to legend,
the first Istanbul coffeeshop opened as far back as 1475; the iconic Kiva Han. The truth is it was
probably built at least a little while later, but who cares? It would be part of a movement
that would change the world, and set us on a course leading all the way to the present.
Basically, in the past coffee was a drink. That’s it. Something you consume.
But in Istanbul it would become a way of life. By the time we find accounts of Turkish cafes,
we read of enormous spaces, bright and open, buzzing with people and energy. The air was
rich with the smell of roasting coffee, and loud- echoing with crowds laughing, gossiping,
talking politics or playing games like chess or backgammon. Sometimes there would be a band
or musician on stage, or a poet doing a reading. And there were no private tables; everyone shared
a floor together, regardless of rank or status. It turned out coffee didn’t just give energy for
fighting or dancing- it was equally effective at sparking conversation,
and before long Istanbul’s cafes became known as “street universities,” or “schools of the wise.”
And the entire culture of the empire would shift dramatically. In these cafes artists
would debut new works and find inspiration. New forms of theater and literature would develop,
and the brightest minds in academics could meet and share ideas freely, outside of the
structured order of government and university. It was not a coincidence that the rise in
Istanbul’s cafes aligned exactly with the Ottoman Golden Age in the years of Suleiman
the Magnificent, and it was also not a coincidence that in 1538, Suleiman would invade and conquer
Yemen, and seize control of al-Mocha. And for the next hundred years it
would be the Turks, not the Yemenis, profiting from the coffee monopoly.
Anyway let’s go back to those cafes. At some point, late in the 16th century,
it started dawning on Ottoman rulers- especially those who were not “magnificent”- that centers of
free speech might be dangerous. And we start to see crackdowns and even a few short-lived bans.
But none of it would actually stick until 1633 when Sultan Murad IV- terribly unpopular and
terrified of being overthrown- declared with no warning that visiting a cafe was now a
capital offense. There would be no public meetings, no unauthorized gatherings and
absolutely no coffee whatsoever. But that is not the crazy part.
No the crazy part is that Murad IV was so paranoid that he used to get incredibly drunk,
dress up as a beggar, walk through the streets of Istanbul and personally hunt for anyone violating
the new law. Whenever he would catch the smell of coffee, or see any person having a sip, he would
rip off his shawl, announce his true identity and then cut off their head with his own sword.
Thankfully the Sultan would die at the age of 27 from cirrhosis;
all those drunken nights catching up to him quickly, and Istanbul’s café scene would recover.
Let’s take a break for some Turkish coffee.
There are few things on earth like a café in Istanbul. But we are not in Istanbul,
we’re in Bangkok, so we’re making due by visiting the house of a Turkish family, recently converted
into a home-style restaurant.
The most common legend about Turkish coffee is that its method was developed in Suleiman’s
royal palace. In the past, Turkish coffee had been prepared just like in Yemen,
which itself was adapted almost entirely from Ethiopia. But Suleiman was so fascinated by
this new drink he appointed a coffee master- assisted by a team of 40 roasters, grinders,
and brewers and that led to this. The idea of Turkish coffee is to grind the beans
into a fine powder- much finer than modern coffee grounds. Then to heat it with water
and stir to create a rich and thick froth without burning the beans. And while today
technology has advanced the basic concept is the same- and every cup tells a story
of history. The taste and superstitions we might have found in Istanbul 500 years ago.
Ok. I think- what
is it? That looks like the Taj Mahal. Business. Ok. It’s a fish again. You’re
just seeing fish. Always good. Fish is always good! It’s abundance. Fish is abundance. Yeah. Is
it a fish? I mean…corn?  It looks like a bat hanging upside down. Well, you’re also looking
from the other angle. It’s right side up to us. Ooh, that’s a bat. In Rorschach tests, I would
fail. It’s just blips for me. A dog! Dog? Look. Nose, ears… Have you ever seen a dog before? Goofy
the Dog. A woman? You see a woman? Adam! Business. You see anything else? I think that’s a cut.
In the heyday of Istanbul’s café scene, with the Turkish economy booming,
Suleiman the Magnificent went on the warpath, capturing Yemen and a whole lot more.
As early as 1521 he’d established a foothold in Europe, taking Belgrade of today’s Serbia,
where immediately a coffeeshop would open- the first ever on European soil. And this would repeat
itself over and over as the Ottomans pushed west. The Turkish style of coffee, thick, unfiltered,
the stuff we just had at the last restaurant- well wherever you find something that looks like that,
you’re probably in the old Ottoman territory. Turkish coffee would become the style consumed
to this day in the Balkans, Ukraine, and Greece, all thanks to the conquests of Suleiman.
And the Ottoman expansion is also how the word became standardized everywhere- Yemeni
“Gahwah” becoming Turkish “Kahve” which would be the root of coffee and café.
Anyway speaking of cafes, the Turks might have introduced the idea of coffeeshops as
places for gathering, but there were still a few major elements missing from what we know today.
And that brings us past the Ottoman borders and into western Europe.
Coffee might have arrived on European soil in the 1520s, but given the intense distrust between the
Christian West and the Ottoman Turks, this would go unnoticed on the rest of the continent for a
very long time. The first actual record of coffee in Western writing comes in 1582, when a German
doctor tried it on a visit to Aleppo, describing it as a black beverage good for digestion.
Nine years later coffee would be introduced to Venetian traders,
who bought a few bags from Istanbul and pitched it as a medicine. But this would be a hard sell;
after all, word began to spread that this was a Muslim delicacy, and that was problematic.
Cardinals in the Vatican lobbied the Pope, Clement VIII, to ban coffee outright- to make it illegal
for Christian consumers. But the Pope decided he should try it before making any judgements
and in 1600, he famously had a taste, liked it and gave coffee the papal seal of approval.
Just like Kaldi and the goats, this is a famous story. And it is true- but it didn’t actually
matter, because the bigger problem wasn’t God, it was money. The Ottomans still held
a monopoly from al-Mocha, and their prices were so high that coffee was out of reach
to all but the wealthiest foreign customers. It would take another four decades after the
Pope’s blessing for the first café to open in Western Europe, and that was only after
the Ottomans were kicked out of Yemen in a 1638 uprising. Finally in control of their own country,
the Yemeni people and the new Qasimid Dynasty set out to build a new economy
based on selling lots and lots of coffee, and re-opened trade links with the West.
The first café in Christian Europe would open in Venice in 1645, and before long
the floodgates would open; coffeeshops in Italy followed by more in England, Germany,
France, the Netherlands and beyond. And the impact on life in Europe would be monumental.
In Austria, the Viennese introduced the idea of filtering coffee, and serving it
with sides like cream and sugar. The Austrians also pioneered the sale of coffeeshop pastries,
debuting the Kipferl in the 1680s, which would eventually become the croissant.
Soon enough bakers everywhere were adding their own specialties to local cafes; brioche with nuts
and raisins first made in Germany and sold as coffeecake, and the cinnamon bun debuted
in the coffeeshops of Stockholm, Sweden. Cafes would become the center of social
life in France, cradles of music in what’s now Germany and the Netherlands but most of
all when we are talking about 17th century coffeeshops, this is a story about London.
It is very difficult to express how significant the café became to everyday
life in England. As just a few examples- there was one coffeeshop owned by a guy named Edward Lloyd,
where boat captains and merchants used to meet up and talk about conditions at sea.
This would evolve into Lloyds of London, the legendary insurance marketplace. And speaking
of markets, John Castaing used to post up at Jonathan’s Coffeeshop, where he would
update patrons on the day’s commodities pricing, eventually growing into the London Stock Exchange.
By the way, Jonathan’s Coffeeshop would also gain notoriety as the hangout for Voltaire after his
expulsion from France. In that café he became friends with the niece of Isaac Newton, who told
him a story about her uncle and an apple falling from a tree. Voltaire scribbled this on a napkin
and he would publish the tale to great fanfare. As for Isaac Newton himself, well his hangout
was a different London Café, the Grecian, where he would famously stay up long hours drinking
coffee with Edmund Halley and other academic titans, together formulating theories that
would change our knowledge of math and science. We are by no means done. In the early 1700s,
customers in London Cafes began bringing in items for sale- paintings, rare books
and imported pottery. A system would begin where someone would light a small candle and customers
could make offers for whatever was for sale; when the candle burned out, the highest offer won. Not
only would this create the modern auction, but the world’s most famous auction houses, Sotheby’s and
Christies, both began inside London coffeeshops. And so did prominent magazines and newspapers-
The Spectator and the Tatler as two examples, both not just created for café customers but actually,
at least in the beginning, written in coffeeshops. Cafes in London served as post offices. When ships
were about to sail overseas, captains would hang a bag on the wall of their favorite café with the
name of the destination, and anyone could drop off a letter or package for shipping for a small fee.
And speaking of small fees, it was in these establishments where baristas
first placed cups on the counter, labeled “T.I.P.S.”…at least according to legend,
“To Insure Prompt Service.” The first tip jars. Anyway. With so much of English and European
culture moving out of traditional spaces and into cafes, it wouldn’t take long
before the pushback would begin. And that brings us to the next part of this story.
In spite of all the advancements in coffee culture, the 1660s were not a great time to be
in London. A massive Bubonic Plague epidemic swept through town in 1664 and ’65, and as soon as that
was under control, the Great Fire of London pretty much leveled everything inside the city walls.
Now none of this was the fault of the king, Charles II, but since it happened on his watch
he began to worry about public perception. To placate the people he introduced radical
reforms granting religious freedom. A nice idea. But instead of calming things down it would set
off a furor where radicals in each group started blaming the king for supporting their enemies, and
King Charles would descend into full-on paranoia. Terrified that everyone was plotting against him,
in 1675 the king would issue an order to shut down all of England’s cafes, to put an end to
socializing. This did not go over well. So intense would be the backlash that just eleven days later
he would back down and rescind the order, then live out his days in terror of enemies all around.
King Charles II, and Murad IV in Turkey were not completely off base in assuming coffeeshops were
centers of anti-government radicalism. They were- and not just because of all the people coming
together to socialize. That had been happening since the beginning of time, but in the past the
drink of choice was beer, and beer kept the masses drunk, unfocused, and unthreatening- at least
to those in power. But coffee had the opposite effect and all of a sudden, people were thinking,
and to an unelected leader, thinking is dangerous. As coffee spread across the old world there would
be countless attempts at crackdowns and regulations, negative PR campaigns and
full-on bans- see our story from the open about Johan Sebastian Bach. And while we need to move
on here are two more insane examples. The first takes us to Prussia,
where Frederick the Great was not a fan of coffee, and especially began to worry that it
was infiltrating the peasant class, who he relied on for blind support of all of his foreign wars.
So not only did he outlaw imported coffee, but he went as far as to hire 400 combat veterans to
patrol the streets of Prussian cities, literally smelling the air to try to detect the scent of
illicit coffee being roasted. These men would be known as Prussia’s Kaffeeschnuffler, or coffee
sniffers, and that is still less ridiculous than the next story, which comes from Sweden.
In this case, the anti-coffee-monarch was King Gustav III, who really wanted to ban
coffee but worried about the public reaction. So he set out to prove that coffee was toxic,
so no one could argue when he outlawed cafes. As an experiment he found a pair of identical
twins who had committed a murder and were both sentenced to death.
The king offered to commute their sentences to life in prison, with the caveat that for the
rest of their lives one must drink three pots of coffee a day, and the other could only drink tea.
The idea was to prove that tea was safe and coffee was not. This would fail. Both brothers
would outlive the king. They’d survive beyond any of the doctors who observed
their condition and to this day Sweden is among the world’s leading coffee-drinking countries.
Anyway I can’t absolutely say for sure that this happened. It feels like a legend. But
honestly who even cares because the moral of the story is an absolute fact. Once coffee
arrived anywhere- it was there to stay. So let’s take a break for a coffee
and a croissant.
The modern coffeeshop- with its shelf of pastries, selection of coffee drinks and lively atmosphere-
takes bits and pieces from much of the world. Mecca, Istanbul, Stockholm and London…but one
could say the real point of origin when it all turned into this goes back to 1837,
when a Viennese businessman named August Zang moved to Paris and opened a bakery. He’d introduce
to France the Austrian technique of steam baking- basically injecting steam into the hot
oven to keep dough soft and fluffy while the crust hardens. Allowing the innovation of the baguette,
the croissant, and the entire category of French pastry. It wasn’t long before these
would spread to Parisian cafes, along with the Austrian style of adding dense whipped cream
to strong coffee- what the French would call Café Viennois. Then soon enough more coffee
and dairy combinations would emerge intended to pair with pastries and the whole world’s morning
culture would change.
So I’m an iced Americano drinker, and I understand that purists would say that
that’s the incorrect way to drink coffee, but we live in Thailand. We’re in the tropics. I
don’t know how you can drink hot coffee. No, I’m a purist, there is no other way
to drink coffee. I’m not arguing with you, that is probably- mine gets watered down,
yours doesn’t, I understand you’re probably drinking more pure-tasting coffee than I am.
But we’re taping this in Bangkok, don’t judge me, it is really, really, really hot. I don’t
know what should happen for me to drink cold coffee. I don’t think I’ve had a sip of…I’ve
bought a cold coffee in years. Yeah- but iced Americano, hot Americano…pastry…meringue…Meringue,
because I’m watching my figure for my boyfriend. Who’s he? That was a reference! From a TV show.
“Ok, Jan.” No? Ok, I’m going to show it to you. George Glass! My boyfriend. I’m so lost
right now. George Tropicana. I’ll show it to you, ok? Are you OK? Are you having a stroke?
In the year 1616, thirty years before the first café would open in Venice,
the Dutch sent a spy into Yemen to try to smuggle out some coffee and break the monopoly.
The name of this sailor was Pieter van den Broecke. And if that name sounds familiar
that is the exact same guy who would later set up the first nutmeg plantation on the
Banda Islands. We literally interviewed his great-great-great-whatever grandson. And
somehow we never realized his connection to coffee because it would be pretty much lost to history.
Basically Mr. Van den Broecke would actually succeed and manage to sneak out
a few raw coffee beans from al-Mocha. He’d bring them back to Amsterdam,
but coffee doesn’t grow in the Dutch climate, so nothing would happen. At first.
Now- I cannot express how wild this is- but somehow botanists at the Amsterdam
Botanical Gardens for the next eight decades managed to keep these coffee plants alive in
a small greenhouse. And then in 1696, half a century after Pieter van den Broecke had died,
a few cuttings of these plants were brought along on a boat sailing halfway around the
world to the Dutch colony of Java. And the coffee industry would change forever.
In 1711 the first shipment of Dutch coffee, grown in Indonesia would reach the European market,
and this would prove so successful, so in demand that within one single decade two-thirds of the
global coffee trade was coming from Java. And after 260 years, the al-Mocha monopoly was over.
This would lead to a lot of consequences. For one thing, the price of coffee plummeted,
which led to the profusion of more cafes and the rise of home coffee consumption.
The economy of Yemen collapsed; since the Dutch relied on slaves, their coffee was cheaper;
Yemen could not compete, and the country fell into a depression. Within a generation most of
the old coffee farms were gone; abandoned or replaced with other crops like Khat,
a stimulant chewed for a quick buzz. Then there would be the fallout for
the Javanese, the native people of the island. Since the Indonesian colony
was governed not by Holland but by the Dutch East India Company, a for-profit enterprise,
coffee became a key commodity- and that meant a lot of forced labor, exploitation, ecological
disaster and full-on massacres, the worst carried out against the Sundanese of West Java; entire
villages executed for coming in below quota. Just like everything about the Dutch East Indies,
the coffee trade was awful. But there was one interesting legacy that came from the harsh
treatment of the local people. The Indonesian farmers were banned from drinking coffee;
every bean was money meant for export. But at some point somebody noticed that a native animal,
the Asian palm civet, fed on coffee plants and seemed to eat only the best quality berries.
Then the civet would digest the fruit but not the bean, which would pass through their system
and be collected, the farmers keeping them for special occasions and creating what we now call
Kopi Luwak, the world’s most expensive coffee. Anyway in time the Dutch would expand their coffee
production to other parts of Indonesia; to Sumatra and Borneo and Sulawesi- but on that island they
found something unexpected…coffee. Already there. And that is another fascinating story.
Now I’m going to start by saying this is a legend. I have no idea if it’s true. There are
a lot of different versions online and in old writing. But the gist of it is that sometime,
probably in the 1500s, a Muslim from India named Baba Budan took a pilgrimage to Mecca. On his way
home he traveled through Yemen, heading towards the port to catch his ship. He fell in love with
coffee, and since he knew it did not exist in India, he stole exactly seven raw coffee beans
and hid them in his beard, then planted them in the hills of Karnataka, his home province,
and thus would begin the Indian coffee industry. The story goes that some south Indian sailor must
have brought some coffee along on a trading voyage to Sulawesi, and that’s how the plant arrived.
Again I have no idea if this story is true. But I don’t have a better explanation,
and it’s also worth mentioning that in the 1840s British colonists deep in the
hills of Karnataka found coffee plantations that apparently had been there for a very long time.
Anyway. The Dutch
dominance in the global coffee industry would be short-lived. And that was because of what might be
the costliest present in global farming history. In 1714, as a token of friendship to celebrate the
end of the War of Spanish Succession, the mayor of Amsterdam, a Mr. Nicolaas Witsen, presented
one single coffee tree as a gift to Louis XIV, the King of France. The king was over the moon- this
was among the rarest items in the Western world…so he showed it off to the public, and had a special
greenhouse constructed just to keep it safe. Nine years later, across the Atlantic on the
island of Martinique, a highborn French soldier named Gabriel de Clieu was about to head home
at the end of his rotation. Somehow he heard a rumor that the Dutch were having some success
planting coffee in the New World, so he came up with an idea. De Clieu hatched a plan to use a
family connection at the palace to sneak into what was now Louis XV’s greenhouse and cut a
single seedling from the royal plant. Then if all went well, he would smuggle it back to Martinique,
keep it alive on the dangerous ocean crossing, somehow grow it into a massive plantation and
become a national hero. In the end, that is exactly what would happen.
So incredibly well would this plant take to Martinique that within a generation,
Martinique and the rest of the French New World colonies supplied more than half of all the
coffee sold across the entire global market. But just like for the Dutch this was not to
last. In 1727, the Portuguese in Brazil decided they wanted a piece of the action. So they sent
an envoy to French Guyana to negotiate the price for a plant. The Guyanese governor said
absolutely not, our coffee is not for sale. But this is when I should mention that the envoy,
a Mr. Francisco de Melo Palheta, was very handsome. Apparently legendarily handsome,
and in his time in Cayenne he made quite an impression on the Governor’s wife. And when he
left, she presented him with a bouquet of flowers with a few raw coffee beans hidden in the bottom.
And that was how the Brazilian coffee industry would start- to this day still the biggest in
the world. With the Portuguese and Dutch now in possession of coffee the French
said  it and agreed to sell some to the English, in Jamaica, where in 1728 they’d
plant what is now known as Blue Mountain. Within the next few years, coffee farming
would expand to Cuba, Mexico, El Salvador, Costa Rica, pretty much all across the American tropics
and all of it- literally almost all the coffee ever farmed in the entire western hemisphere-
descended from that one single plant smuggled from Louis XV’s palace. A plant that itself descended
from one single raw coffee bean stolen from Yemen by Pieter Van den Broecke. And that raw coffee
bean belonged to a plant once taken across the Red Sea directly from the Oromo traders of Ethiopia.
I think it’s time for a coffee.
It’s easy to follow the spread of European colonialism and see how coffee reached a
huge part of the world- the tropics of the Americas, sub-Saharan Africa and here in
Southeast Asia. Anywhere the climate was suitable, by the late 19th century coffee
was probably growing. But that doesn’t mean it immediately became part of the native culture.
In some cases that was by force. Like how the Dutch banned the Indonesian locals from
drinking coffee, so too did the British pass laws against the Kenyans, with even one unauthorized
coffee tree enough for a prison sentence. Never mind the fact that coffee in Kenya grows wild.
Sometimes coffee wasn’t quote-illegal; it was just strictly segregated and kept far away
from local people- French Indochina as a classic example, even as Vietnam’s coffee farms exploded.
And then there were places like Hong Kong where coffee was around, it just didn’t suit
the local palate, until new innovations started to change the native perception.
The decades between the early 20th century and the end of the colonial
era were kind of a third coffee “Big Bang”- local people from one side of the planet
to the other adding their own flavors and techniques to coffee, and in the process,
making something once forbidden completely their own. As just one example take the Malaysian and
Singaporean Kopitiam. Beginning with the Hainanese domestic workers in British colonial households,
introduced to the public in the 1920s, developing over time into a brand new category. Coffee beans
roasted with sugar, butter and salt, cut with wheat or dried corn to make the mixture more
affordable. Then add in some condensed milk or mix half-and-half with tea and you have the start of a
perfect Malaysian morning.
Ok. We are reaching the point in the shoot when if I don’t keep drinking coffee at the same rate
that we have since we started, I’m going to crash, and it’s all going to be over. So…I
can barely pick it up! What are you drinking? I have Kopi- regular coffee I think? It’s coffee
with milk. There is Kopi O, Kopi something…mine is just regular. With the condensed milk. So yours
is the Malaysian proper kopitiam coffee. Mine is “cham”. It’s hard to drink this- it’s so frothy,
the Malaysian way of making coffee- it’s so hard with a mustache. This is… This is Cham,
it’s half coffee, half tea. A kopitiam staple. This is sort of the first wave of coffeeshops
that were for the public in Southeast Asia. The beginning of the coffee story starts with the
colonists. It took a very long time before it was accepted by or presented to the actual people who
are from here. But it started in Singapore and Malaysia with the kopitiam culture,
which is what would influence Thailand. We’ve done a whole lot on that on the channel before,
I’ll link that in the top pinned comment. I’m consciously slowing myself down as I
talk. I have this- if I could start…I love living in Bangkok, I love our life where it
is right now. But Malaysian mornings, to start in a kopitiam- to me, that’s
the best possible start to a day. I’m just like …I’m in between my coffee kicks now.
So I find this almost subversive. Like, when the whole coffee culture started in Southeast Asia,
not for colonists but for the actual people- it kind of almost started as rebellion. Like…in
Malaysia- we’re at a kopitiam right now- Malaysia and Singapore, that was one side of the story,
obviously which we’ve covered here on the channel before, but the domestic workers in
the English households, who learned the recipes for coffee, toast- this is with the “kaya”, which
is a coconut custard that was first influenced by the Portuguese when they were the colonists. It’s
such an interesting story…we see the same thing in Hong Kong, where the chachaanteng culture,
which translates to “tea house,” but it’s very coffee-focused, and chachaanteng culture in
Hong Kong also started with “how do we take these dishes that we’re almost prohibited from eating,
or drinks that we’re prohibited from having, and present them in a way that’s affordable to the
masses.” Macaroni with ketchup. Deep-fried peanut butter French toast. And then obviously Vietnam is
the classic example, because how everything was adapted for local people in rebellion against
the French banning them from having coffee. It’s such an interesting chapter in history,
and don’t underestimate the coffee culture in Southeast Asia. It’s absolutely phenomenal,
and I’m just going to keep rambling, because I’ve had a bunch of coffee and
I can’t stop myself.
If you’ve watched these videos before you probably know what’s coming next.
Monoculture farming- in this case an extreme example, pretty much always ends the same
way- with some awful pest or disease that rips through the global harvest.
In the case of coffee it was a fungus, first identified in 1869 in Sri Lanka and quickly
devastating the entire local industry. Then from there it would spread to India,
then Southeast Asia, and soon the entire Eastern Hemisphere was in trouble.
Now at first there was nothing anyone could do. Plantation owners switched to growing tea,
and all across Europe tea consumption skyrocketed; coffeeshops rebranding as teahouses. For the last
two decades of the 19th century coffee became essentially a New World drink,
grown and consumed pretty much only in the west, where the blight thankfully did not take hold.
But then in 1895 a French botanist realized that the people in Central Africa- what’s
now Gabon and the Democratic Republic of the Congo- were growing and consuming a native
strain of coffee that was not the same as the one the rest of the world knew.
It turned out this varietal grew in lowlands, tolerating high heat- perfect for the Asian
tropics. And even better, it was almost completely resistant to the devastating
coffee fungus. At first this new strain would be given the name Coffea canephora,
but in 1900 at the Paris World’s Fair it would be introduced to the world as “Robusta,” and
the old varietal, what had been called Mocha or simply “coffee”, came to be known as “Arabica.”
Now- robusta coffee is very different from Arabica. It’s more bitter, has a stronger
flavor and pretty soon, scientists realized it could hold up to freeze-drying or preserving
in ways Arabica could not. And so the instant coffee revolution would kick into high gear.
The idea for making a fast packet-coffee started as far back as 1881, with a French soldier named
Alphonse Allais who found himself frustrated with the coffee rations on the battlefield, so he
developed a method of dehydrating brewed coffee. But his invention was grainy and hard to drink,
so enter David Strang of New Zealand, who came up with a water-soluble coffee powder in 1890.
A few years later this would be perfected by Satori Kato, from Japan working in Chicago, who
made that powder shelf-stable and long-lasting. And finally after the introduction of Robusta,
this would be turned into a commercial product by George Washington- a different George Washington,
this one born in Belgium, working in Brooklyn. Washington’s coffee would be bought out by the
United States Army during World War I where it was given the slang name “George,” as in,
a cup of George. How that eventually turned into a cup of Joe has been entirely lost to history.
Anyway all these early versions of instant coffee still had to be brewed- boiled and filtered- and
they weren’t really “instant.” Until in 1938 a Swiss chemist named Max Morgenthaler pioneered
a truly revolutionary version- blending coffee extract with added carbohydrates to make something
fast, efficient and packed with flavor. This would be introduced by Nestle as “Nescafe”.
Now at the same time as instant coffee was coming into existence, a parallel movement
was focused on increasing speed and quality at the same time. This would be centered in Italy,
starting in 1884 when Angelo Moriondo of Torino built the first-ever steam-powered coffee machine.
In 1901 this would be advanced by Luigi Bezzera of Milan, who refined the concept so it could
brew single portions, one-by-one. Bezzera’s patent would be sold to an engineer named
Desiderio Pavoni, who added some upgrades and then in 1906 introduced the machine and
the concept of Espresso to the world. Believe it or not it wasn’t until 1947
when espresso machines would be refined enough to start adding milk or cream into the brew, opening
the door to stuff like cappuccino, café Latte and pretty much the entire modern category of coffee.
As for the Americano, by the way, that also shows up around the same time in Italy- named for the
American soldiers stationed after World War II who wanted their espresso watered down to taste
more like the drip coffee they favored back home. Though it should be mentioned that drip coffee is
not an American invention- that credit goes to a humble German housewife named Melitta Bentz,
who in 1908 punched some holes in the bottom of a brass pot, lined it with a
sheet of paper from her son’s school notebook and found the result to be very satisfying.
Mrs. Bentz, by the way, would patent this invention, set up a company to
mass-produce her creation and to this day Melitta is one of the world’s largest
manufacturers of coffee-related accessories. Anyway. One last note before we move on.
In case all this time you’ve been wondering why “mocha” today means coffee mixed with chocolate,
that starts in the United States in the early 20th century with a craze for coffee-flavored sweets,
especially cake frosting. This became known as Mocha cake, and to give it a bit more sweetness
it became common for chocolate to be added into the recipe. The combination of coffee
and chocolate would catch on and soon enough was applied to a drink, and that is where the
new definition of Mocha came from. Let’s take one last coffee break.
A few last odds and ends
before we move on. The coffee styles we see most often all around the world might have taken their
current form after World War II. But the seeds at least in some cases were planted much earlier.
The Cappuccino first shows up at least in name in 18th century Austria, the combination of milk
and coffee said to resemble the brown robes of Capuchin monks. Hence the original term Kapuziner.
Contrary to popular belief it is not Italian. That’s because around the same time in Italy the
identical recipe took on its own name…Café Latte. There are some coffee styles that don’t show up
until decades after the espresso revolution. The Cortado, for example, comes from 1960s Spain,
with workers asking for their espresso to be cut- or cortar- with a bit of milk.
The Long Black first appears in the 1950s, and the Flat White in the mid ‘80s. Both
the subject of fierce argument between Australia and New Zealand- heated enough
that they deserve their own video one day. It’s not a style of coffee but while we’re here
let’s mention decaf- that shows up in 1903 when a German coffee seller received some beans that
had been submerged in seawater- surprisingly keeping their flavor but not their caffeine.
And finally the modern pour-over…well that goes back to Melitta Bentz herself;
the modern hand-pour revolution taking hold in Japan in the late 1990s.
So, I’m going to make this very fast because
I am consciously trying to not speak at a thousand miles an hour after all the coffee, but…saving the
best for last. I think in Bangkok, this is- if it hasn’t been clear already, Daria is the coffee
expert, not me. I’m the 7-11 coffee drinker as unfortunately you have seen on the channel
many times in the past. Daria, who has probably experimented with every coffee shop in Bangkok,
this is your…this is where you go. So what we’re drinking right now…mine is what you’d call
pour-over coffee? Drip coffee? Not drip- different context. This is Ethiopian Raga Raru, which comes
from the highlands, I was looking it up. This- many people, if you’re into artisan coffee, you
know Yerga Cheffe, which is a very famous coffee growing area in Ethiopia, that’s where this is
from. Daria’s is a Peruvian blend. Did you learn this yesterday? I learned it right now. I Googled
it- I literally have Google Maps open on my phone, I was checking where- don’t give away the game
. Alright. I wanted to ask Daria while we’re here, just thinking about this…this
profusion of coffee, artisan coffee where you can choose your own palate or your own style,
does anything stand out in your memory? I’m asking this for a reason. A café that you’ve
been to anywhere in our travels, filming or otherwise, that you just thought was a really
cool place? There are a couple places that come first to my mind. Do you remember Soloist in
Beijing? Ooh yeah, I think I introduced that to you. What a great place. One of the first
artisanal places in Beijing. Before China’s coffee culture, they were one of the first to actually
do it well, and they also- yeah, overlooking Tiananmen. Not overlooking- but it kind of was,
it was right there, like a block from Tiananmen, it was the first place I ever had to wait a
long time for a coffee. Yeah exactly. And that made you angry? At first, and then I tried it,
and it was great. This was probably the first one that comes up to my mind. Graph,
from Chiang Mai. Next time we’re in Chiang Mai we definitely need to go there. They’re definitely
one of the trendsetters, one of the best coffee places in Thailand. And Mother Roaster, of course,
one of the first places that we went to for coffee that was like…when I saw her,
I was starstruck. I have a picture with her still where I’m super happy.
I think for me, in Sulawesi, when Dennis and I were there shooting in Makassar, that…we didn’t
get it on camera, we went there after we were filming, but that was the coolest…everything
local, and each coffee had its own way- again, Ohm is off-camera, he’s off-screen,
but it’s interesting how different beans are better prepared in different ways. There are
some things that they would tell you that you need to have it made like “this”- the temperature
of the water- I don’t know, I’m talking about something I don’t really understand, but yeah,
you choose the beans based on how it’s best prepared, yeah? Best way to make it? Again.
Can I eat? You can eat, you can drink. My favorite breakfast place. This is so good.
Dennis, before we stop rolling tape, I’m
going to ask you the same question. I know you’re more of a tea drinker, is there one café that
stands out to you? The Kopitiam in KL? Oh, dude, how good was that? We can call that artisanal…just
because they make it in a tin can, it’s still artisanal. Alright. Mmm. Yeah, go ahead and eat.
I’m already like . If you’re watching this somehow from Bangkok, this is the best plate
of breakfast in the city. I can definitively say that. But I’m going to enjoy my coffee,
then I’m going to crash hard and nap on the couch for the next two hours. Ohm, thanks for having us,
that’s a cut on our final cup of coffee.
Despite what you might assume, the first coffee chains were not American. Depending
on what sources you read the idea of multi-outlet coffeeshops dates back to the early 20th century
in England, or France, or even Japan, and the modern-everything-identical concept was
actually pioneered in Austria, where by the 1920s Aida had a half-dozen locations all serving the
same pastries and drinks in the same style. The first major American café brand was the
memorably named Chock Full O’ Nuts- as you might expect originally a nut shop.
And while chain stores in general do not have the best reputations, in this case,
they were actually a pretty good company. Way before this was normal, they insisted on equal
opportunity hiring- and refused to expand into the South because of laws enforcing segregation. They
paid a living wage and provided all staff with health care and in 1957, hired the civil rights
icon Jackie Robinson to serve as corporate Vice President when his baseball playing career ended.
But that is just a side note because this is obviously about Starbucks.
The biggest coffee empire in world history started in 1971 in Seattle, founded by three friends
and based on a small chain called Peet’s, which they’d loved as students at the University of San
Francisco. They’d name it Starbucks, not because of Moby Dick but because they liked the way the
word sounded. Over the next thirteen years they’d grow to four or five Seattle locations, then sell
their shares in Starbucks to outside investors. Now this sounds like the classic tragic story
of people founding a big company and selling out too early. But that’s actually not what happened.
This is one of the only examples I can think of where somehow everybody actually won. The first
of the Starbucks co-founders, Jerry Baldwin- well he’d use his share of the money to buy out Peet’s,
the brand’s original inspiration, and would grow that business large enough to take it public in
2001. He’s now a Napa Valley winemaker and worth about half a billion dollars.
The second partner, Gordon Bowker, well he’d scale up his side project, Redhook Brewery,
which would also go public after merging with or acquiring a few other pioneering beer companies.
He passed away in 2025 at the age of 82. And finally there was Zev Seigl, who actually
left Starbucks before the sale and set out on a path of serial entrepreneurship, becoming a
well-known business mentor and public speaker. As for Starbucks itself, it would also do pretty
well. Bought out by Howard Schultz, who would lead a push for fast expansion,
then listed as an IPO in 1992. Today there are more than 41,000
Starbucks stores across the world, and you don’t need me to talk much more about Starbucks because
you know what it is, you’ve seen it everywhere, and it is basically the McDonald’s of coffee.
Or actually McDonalds is the McDonalds of coffee, because they are 2nd in the world in
sales- pouring around three billion cups per year in their own worldwide venues. For the record just
in case you’re wondering, the rest of the top 5 are China’s Luckin Coffee, Dunkin’ (formerly
Dunkin Donuts), and Canada’s Tim Horton’s. There are positives about these massive
coffee conglomerates- I’m going to be honest, I love Dunkin’ coffee. But the biggest positive
is probably the response; the pushback against the corporatization of the category. According
to most analysis, the so-called Third Wave started in 1995 with Chicago’s Intelligentsia
Coffee and Durham North Carolina’s Counter Culture Coffee, then soon enough they would be followed by
other artisanal roasters all across the planet- focusing not on sales volume but on supply chain,
flavor, technique and quality and bringing us into an unequivocal coffee golden age.
But that Golden Age might not last much longer. Every year as the climate gets warmer there
is less arable land suitable for coffee farming. This is not alarmism.
This is what is happening right now. In the coffee-growing part of the world,
lowland plantations are already dying out. And to keep up with the suitable temperature range,
farms are moving as much as 500 meters higher in elevation, which means more
land clearing, which reinforces the cycle. At this moment the current prediction from
trade organizations is that by 2050, global coffee production will be reduced by half versus where
it is now, and that is best case scenario. The worst case is apocalyptic. Because of the effect
of climate change on Central and East Africa, the vast majority of wild coffee strains are
either already gone, or in imminent danger of extinction. And that means if there is another
blight, fungus or disease, we are running out of options to find the next Robusta;
the next bean that might save the day. This is not a political issue. This is
not something up for debate, because it’s not theoretical. It is already happening,
and all around the world coffee producers are sounding the alarm.
Now this doesn’t mean that coffee is just all of a sudden going to disappear tomorrow. But it 1000%
does mean we shouldn’t take coffee for granted. This incredible plant that rewrote history,
that sparked so much creativity and innovation, the center of our social and business lives and
something that just makes the world so much more interesting. From the mountains of Ethiopia to the
Arabian Peninsula. The cafes of Istanbul to the coffeeshops of London. From Java to Martinique,
Brazil to Vietnam to wherever you are- coffee deserves its due.
So the next time you order an Espresso Martini, try a shot of Kahlua or a Tenerife Barraquito.
The next time you visit a kopitiam, a diner or an artisan roastery, the next time you enjoy a
Caffe Latte, a Cappuccino, a Mocha or an Americano take just a second to appreciate coffee. Because
honestly- what would we do without it? Subscribe to the channel for more from
OTR. Thank you so much to everyone who supports us on Patreon, it really helps to keep us going.
Find links below to our Patreon and social media, and we’ll see you soon.